Inter High
Day 3
Team Tournament
Semifinals
Spirit!
（審判）はっきよい！
（天王寺(てんのうじ)）うせろ
（選手）ええっ？
Get lost.
（野地(のぢ)）ウオ〜ッ！
（審判）はっきよい！
Spirit!
（観客）うわぁ！
Something seems different about him.
（柴木山(しばきやま)）何かが変わったような…
昨日 あいつに何かしましたか？
Do you have something to do with that?
I didn't do a thing.
（駿海(しゅんかい)）俺は何もしてねえ
They say boys can grow quite a bit
over the course of three days.
“男子 三日 会わざれば
刮目(かつもく)して見よ”なんていうが…
土俵という一瞬の世界を
生きている男は 化けるのも一瞬だ
But sumo bouts can end in a flash,
and the boys in it grow just as fast.
Tennoji, Kuze, and Hinomaru...
天王寺も 久世(くぜ)も 火ノ丸(ひのまる)も—
An ace's growth can spur
the rest of their team.
エースの変化は
周りを… チームを変える
優勝に懸ける強い思いは
どこも同じだが—
Everyone shares the same desire to win.
Ryugeji High School
(Fukuoka)
Eiga University High School
(Saitama)
But only one school can come out on top.
最後に残るのは
１校のみ
Odachi High School
(Chiba)
Tottori Hakuro High School (Tottori)
Bout 18
"How I Win"
The team tournament, semifinal.
（アナウンス）
団体戦 準決勝
On the east side, Odachi High School.
東 大太刀(おおだち)高校
西 鳥取白楼(とっとりはくろう)高校
On the west side,
Tottori Hakuro High School.
Good luck, Dachi High!
（男性Ａ）ダチ高 頑張れ！
Looks like the crowd's backing Dachi High.
（沙田(さだ)）期待されてるね ダチ高
Yeah, but in terms of ability,
Hakuro is in another league.
（荒木(あらき)）けど 実力差で言えば—
やっぱり
白楼のほうが はるかに上だろう
Yeah.
（間宮(まみや)）ああ
合気道の榎木晋太郎(えのきしんたろう)
The aikido practitioner, Enoki Shintaro.
The giant juggernaut, Shuto Masaomi.
巨大怪力 首藤正臣(しゅとうまさおみ)
The Mongolian sumo wrestler with a diverse
set of techniques, Batmönkh Batbayar.
モンゴル相撲の多彩な組み技
バトムンフ･バトバヤル
Plus national treasures Kano Akihira...
更に 国宝 加納彰平(かのうあきひら)に—
and Tennoji Shido.
天王寺獅童(しどう)
If the defeat of their ace Tennoji
had gotten to them,
（真田(さなだ)）せめて エース 天王寺の
敗戦に動揺していれば—
つけいる隙もあったろうが
準々決勝を見るかぎり それもない
they may have been easier pickings.
But from watching their quarterfinal bouts,
it seems like it hasn't.
Dachi High doesn't stand a chance, do they?
（荒木）
ダチ高に勝ち目は なさそうですね
（金盛(かなもり)）勝負に絶対はない
There are no absolutes in competition.
（金盛）それに ダチ高には
鬼丸(おにまる)譲りの心の強さがある
Dachi High has Onimaru's
spirit running through them.
When that spirit erupts,
it may well decide this match.
心を燃やしたときの爆発力が
この勝負のカギを握る
First bout.
（アナウンス）先鋒戦(せんぽうせん) 東 小関(おぜき)君
On the east side, Ozeki-kun.
On the west side, Enoki-kun.
西 榎木君
I don't know anything about
what's in your heart.
（小関）君の胸の内は
ほとんど何も分からない
でも…
But...
（桐仁(きりひと)）榎木が相撲を始めたのは
中学かららしい
It seems Enoki started sumo wrestling
in middle school.
天王寺がいた大阪の中学の相撲部で
He was in the same middle school
sumo club in Osaka as Tennoji.
He most likely enrolled in Hakuro
because Tennoji was going there.
鳥取白楼を選んだのは
天王寺を慕ってのことだろう
（小関）なんとなく分かるよ
君が高ぶらずにいられない理由
I think I understand why
you're so worked up right now.
And I get how much Tennoji means to you.
君にとって
天王寺が どういう存在か
Spirit!
（審判）はっきよい！
Aware of Ozeki’s physical advantage,
he changed his charge's angle and timing.
体格で勝る小関の当たりを
角度とタイミングで…
I knew Ozeki had the inferior technique here,
小関が技術で劣っていることは
分かっていたが…
but he seems to be losing
in fighting spirit, too.
（真田）心でも上を行かれた？
（桐仁）部長…
Captain!
On the third day,
（小関）３日目の白楼は
今日までのように冷静じゃなく—
Hakuro will be heated and wild
instead of calm and collected like now.
もっと激しく来ると思う
それこそ 死にものぐるいでね
They'll be going all-out.
Not because they're worried about us,
それは 俺らを
警戒しているとかじゃなく—
but because Eiga High and Kuze Sosuke
will likely be waiting for them in the final,
その先 決勝で待つであろう—
栄華(えいが)大附属 久世草介(そうすけ)の前に—
and they'll want to give Tennoji
a shot at a rematch.
もう一度
天王寺を連れていくために
It's only natural you'd be fired up.
燃えないわけがないんだ
Tennoji means as much to you
as Ushio means to me!
君にとっての天王寺は
俺にとっての潮(うしお)と同じだから！
（小関）先鋒は俺に行かせてくれ
（桐仁）うん？
Let me fight the first bout.
What's brought this on?
（佑真(ゆうま)）珍しいな
お前が そんなこと言うなんて
You've never asked to go in first before.
（千比路(ちひろ)）大丈夫かよ？
変に気負ってんじゃねえか？
You feeling all right, bro?
Is the pressure getting to you?
いや ただ なんかね
俺が いちばん燃える気がしてさ
No, I just felt that bout
would fire me up the most.
（小関）分かるからこそ—
I know all that, so I won't
let your feelings beat mine!
その気持ちに
負けるわけにはいかない！
Ozeki has the larger frame!
体(たい)は小関が上だ
前褌(まえみつ)を引いて 一気に出ろ！
He can grab the front of
his belt and push him out!
Even though he got hold of his belt,
his arm was pushed away!
廻(まわ)しを取っても 腕を極(き)められる！
体は上？　それが どうした！
He's the bigger fighter. So what?
I've honed this technique so that I can
stand shoulder-to-shoulder with Shido-san!
僕は この技で 獅童さんの
横に立つ資格を勝ち取った男だ！
It's my turn to save him!
今度は僕が 獅童さんを救うんだ！
Five years ago
（榎木）ウワッ！　ウッ…
（天王寺）おっと…　すんまへん
Whoops, sorry.
Oh, if it ain't Enoki. You okay?
…て 榎木かい　大丈夫か？
Second-year Tennoji-san, the sumo club's ace?
相撲部の２年生
エース 天王寺さん！
Club Resignation
What's this? You're leaving the sumo club?
なんや お前
相撲部 辞めんのか？
I joined because I was in a local
sumo tournament in elementary school,
（榎木）小学校のころ—
地元の相撲大会に出たのが
きっかけで 興味はあったんです
and I really got into it.
But when I started middle school,
でも 中学で始めるには
ウチの相撲部は—
I found out our sumo club had lots
of members, and skilled ones at that.
部員も多くて レベルも高い
僕は体も細いし…
I'm thin as a rake and Coach seems
to focus more on the bigger kids.
先生も 大きいヤツらを
贔屓(ひいき)にしてるようで…
I see.
（天王寺）
そうか　新入部員の中では—
To me, you looked like one of
our most promising new recruits.
お前に
わりと期待しとったんやけどな
えっ？　い… いや ウソだ
今日 初めて話したのに…
N-No... you can't mean that...
This is the first time we've spoken.
You've trained in a martial art
before, haven't you?
お前 何か格闘技
やっとったやろう？　組み技系の
Something involving grabbing.
A-A little aikido.
あ… 合気道を少し
けど かじった程度で
But not very much.
I didn't tell anyone about that.
How did he know?
誰にも言ったことがないのに
どうして？
You were a beginner,
（天王寺）お前…
初めていうわりに 受け身と
すり足が身に着いとったし—
but you already knew how to
take a hit and move your feet.
I was also wondering
why your wrists were so strong.
手首が強いのも気になっとった
前さばきも独特や
Your frontal defense is very unique, too.
That's not...
（榎木）そんなこと…
Everyone says I don't have
a talent for it, and they're right.
みんなの言うとおり
僕には才能がないんです
It took me six months to realize...
半年やって分かりました
I don't think I like sumo.
僕 相撲を
あんまり好きじゃないみたいです
Some idiots look but don't see,
and there's nothing you can do about that.
（天王寺）見る目のないアホは
おるよ　それは しゃあない
But...
ただ いちばんアホなんは お前や
You're the bigger idiot here.
（天王寺）
周りが お前を強くするんやない
It isn't the people around you
who make you stronger.
You have to do that all by yourself.
己を強くするんは己自身や
Why don't you try doing
some more aikido training?
合気道を
真剣に習ってみたら どうや？
It might end up making you better at sumo.
相撲のほうも伸びるかも分からんで
（天王寺）
まあ でも 決めるんは お前や
Well, the ball's in your court.
If you're set on quitting, go right ahead.
ほんまに辞めたかったら
好きにせえ
ただ お前は
相撲 好きやと思うけどな
But if you ask me, I think you do like sumo.
I can tell.
見て分かるわ　強くなったら
今より もっとハマるで
If you get stronger, you'll like it even more.
だって 今 俺
相撲 めっちゃ おもろいもん！
After all...
I'm having a ton of fun with sumo.
I don't know how serious he was
about stopping me from quitting.
（榎木）
どこまで本気で 僕のことを
引き止めたのかは分からない
でも これだけは言える
But I know this much...
Those words Shido-san said to me
あのとき 獅童さんの
言葉があったから 僕は…
are what made me stronger!
強くなれました
もし あのまま辞めてたら
死ぬほど後悔してたと思う
If I'd quit, I would've sorely regretted it.
Because... I do love sumo, after all!
だって 僕 やっぱり—
死ぬほど 相撲 好きでしたから！
I've only come this far because
I've been chasing after Shido-san.
（榎木）
獅童さんの背中を追ってきたから
僕は ここまで来れたんですよ
I know it's the same for you, Ozeki-san.
そして あんたも きっと
そうなんだろう？　小関さん
But we're not the same, you and I.
でも 同じじゃない
Unlike you, I've spent five years
こちとら強豪校で—
chasing after him in powerhouse schools!
５年も背中を追い続けてんだ！
He got both arms underneath!
（荒木）もろ差し！
（間宮）深い！
He's in close!
You can't beat me with
your body and spirit alone!
心と体だけで勝てるほど
僕の相撲は軽くないんだよ！
My sumo isn't that trivial!
He's getting in low,
and Ozeki's hips are high.
完全に下に入られて
小関の腰が浮いている
It's no good!
ダメだ！　止まらない！
He can't push back.
技とは対人稽古で鍛えられるものだ
You develop technique by
facing numerous opponents.
The captain has trained
on his own for so long,
ずっと１人で
やってきた部長には—
ほとんど
それを磨くことはできなかった
he hasn't had the chance to develop his.
But for that same reason...
でも だからこそ…
That's it, Captain!
（火ノ丸）そこじゃ 部長！
（佑真）いけー！
Go!
（桐仁）技こそが部長の伸びしろ！
...his techniques will improve very quickly!
I was all on my own until this year.
（小関）去年までは１人だった
でも 今の俺には
技を磨き合う仲間たちがいる
Now, I have teammates who
can help improve my technique.
I'll use this technique that
my team and I worked on...
みんなと磨いた この技で
夢をつかむ！
to seize my dream!
We're gonna get Shido-san into
the ring with Kuze Sosuke again!
（榎木）
僕は もう一度 獅童さんを—
久世草介の前に
連れていってみせます！
I won't go down so easily!
（榎木）
このまま終わらせはしない！
I'll come out victorious tomorrow.
あしたは 僕 必ず勝ちますから
I can't do it on my own.
（天王寺）俺１人じゃ行けんのや
I'm counting on you, Shintaro.
頼むで 晋太郎
I'm gonna put it back on his face...
僕が取り戻す！
The smile of a champion!
（榎木）王者の笑みを！
（千鶴子(ちづこ)･礼奈(れいな)）ハッ…
（一同）あっ！
West side wins!
（審判）西の勝ち！
Yes!
（男性）いい試合だった！
That was great sumo.
（火ノ丸）いい相撲じゃった
（小関）うん？
We've taken your feelings onboard.
部長の思い
ワシら しかと受け取ったぞ
Leave the rest to us!
あとは任せろ！
Well done, Enoki.
（加納）いい仕事をしたぜ 榎木
このまま いくぞ
Let's keep this going.
Yes, yes!
I see. So this is what the high
school team tournament is like.
（駿海）なるほど
これが高校相撲 団体戦か
たぎるじゃねえか
It really gets the blood pumping.
Both schools have a burning desire
to see their champions triumphant,
この両校とも
そんな大将への強い思いが—
より一層 互いを奮い立たせている
which is what drives them forward.
Honestly, though, Hakuro
is several degrees stronger...
正直 実力では
白楼が何倍も上だが—
思いを強さに変えたとき—
But when that desire
transforms into strength...
It can cause a major upset.
番狂わせが起こる
What's wrong, Mitsuhashi?
（小関）
どうした？　三ツ橋(みつはし)
I'm wondering what path I'm on.
（蛍(けい)）
本当に これでいいんですかね？
The more I practice these tricks,
邪道といわれる“変化”を
磨けば磨くほど—
そんな僕の
汚い相撲で挙げた１勝を—
the dirtier my sumo becomes.
Is that really what the team wants?
チームは
本当に喜んでくれるだろうか？
I mean, Hinomaru-san prefers
to tackle opponents head-on.
特に 真っ向勝負が信条の
火ノ丸さんの夢へと つながる道を
I wonder if winning using trickery
would taint his dream.
僕の１勝が
汚してしまうんじゃないかって…
You're the type of guy who gets on with it,
not one that agonizes over things.
らしくねえな
お前が弱音を吐くなんて
Huh? I-Is that how you see me?
（蛍）えっ？　ぼ… 僕って
そういうイメージだったんですか？
Sure.
蛍　お前
何か誤解しとるようじゃが—
Kei, you need to realize that the
reverse is a perfectly good technique.
変化も立派な技じゃぞ
えっ？　でも 火ノ丸さんは
絶対 変化をしないじゃないですか
But you never use it, Hinomaru-san.
ああ それはな ワシが変化しても
そこには魂がないからじゃ
Ah, that's because...
I wouldn't be able to
do it with any enthusiasm.
（火ノ丸）
ワシは真っ向勝負が好きで
そのための稽古しかしとらん
I like fighting head-on,
and all my training's geared toward that.
I'd never use a move
I hadn't practiced in a bout.
そんなワシが練習もしない変化を
試合でやってみろ
それは ワシ自身が
積んできた稽古を裏切る行為じゃし
That would go counter
to all the training I'd done,
勝ちに結び付くとは思えん
and I don't think it would help me win.
でも お前は この数か月で—
But these past few months,
you've been practicing the reverse.
勝つために
ひたすら 変化を磨いてきた
You've poured your heart and soul into it.
その技には魂が籠もっておる
佑真が突き押しを
千比路が機動力を磨いたのと同じ
It's no different from Yuma's
strikes or Chihiro's fast feet.
In terms of the reverse,
変化という技に関して お前は
ワシよりスペシャリストなんじゃ
you're a bigger specialist than I am.
Be proud of yourself.
（火ノ丸）胸を張れ
You're thinking, worrying, and practicing
your sumo for the sake of the team.
お前が
チームのために考え 悩み—
磨き上げた その相撲が
ワシにとっては何より誇らしい
Nothing could make me prouder.
He'll probably try a reverse.
（荒木）
ここは さすがに変化スかね？
ダチ高としても
２連敗は 絶対に避けたい
Dachi High will want to avoid
a second loss at all costs.
If Mitsuhashi has a trump card up
his sleeve, now's the time to use it.
三ツ橋も 今まで
温存してきた奇策を出すなら—
ここだろう　ただ…
But...
Against an opponent who
knows his whole move-set,
相手に悟られている この状況で
どうやって
変化を成功させるつもりなのか…
how can he successfully pull off a reverse?
そういえば 真田さん　昨日
三ツ橋と話し込んでましたけど—
By the way, Sanada-san, I saw you
talking with Mitsuhashi yesterday.
何か助言でもしたんですか？
Were you giving him some pointers?
うん？　俺は質問に答えただけだよ
Huh? I just answered his questions.
Hands on the ground.
（審判）手をついて！
Wait!
まだだ！　まだまだ！
Not yet!
（男性Ａ）おお 不成立
A false start.
Of course it was.
（男性Ｂ）そりゃそうだ
明らかに 小さいほう—
That shrimp didn't even have
his hands on the ground.
（男性Ｂ）手ぇついてなかったし
（首藤）ンンッ…
（真田）ンンッ…
（蛍）真田さん
Sanada-san, you jumped the gun when you
faced our captain in the prefecture prelims.
県予選のとき
部長に突っかけてましたよね
Did you do it on purpose?
あれって わざとですか？
Yes, I did.
わざとだよ
（蛍）ンンッ！
（審判）まだだ！
Not yet!
Another false start?
（男性Ａ）また不成立？
（男性Ｂ）何やってんだ！
What are you playing at?
Coach, what's he doing?
監督　これは…
俺は そこまでやれとは
言ってない！
I never told him to do that!
（男性）何だよ！？
（男性）１回で決めろよ！
Let's get on with it already!
You want to know why I did it?
“なんで
そんなことしたんだ”って？
It should be obvious.
そんなの決まってる
俺が弱いからだよ
It's because I'm weak.
I'm weak, so I wanted to
drag him into my zone.
弱いから 死にものぐるいで
自分の土俵に引きずり込みたかった
It didn't matter what anyone
thought of me. I wanted to win.
誰に何と思われようと
勝ちたかったんだよ
You'll do it properly this time. Understood?
（副審）
ちゃんと手をついて　いいね？
Yes, sir.
（蛍）はい　すみません
I'm sorry.
How many times is that now?
（男性Ａ）おい 何回目だ？
（男性Ｂ）わざと やってんのか！
Are you doing this on purpose?
Shuto!
首藤　落ち着いていけ
Stay calm.
I won't do anything.
（首藤）俺は何もしない
I won't let his tricks rattle me.
こいつが何をしようとも動じず—
I'll just wait for him to make a move.
こいつが動くのを待ってから
立てばいい
It didn't matter what anyone though, huh?
（蛍）“誰に何を思われても”…
そうですよね
I see.
I agree.
僕も そう思います
Leaping backwards at the charge?
（千比路）
立ち合いで 後ろに跳ぶ？
Yes.
（蛍）はい
So you momentarily confuse him
and force him to react suddenly.
（千比路）
相手は一瞬 混乱して—
冷静な対処が
できなくなるってことか
It's not a bad plan.
悪くねえ作戦だ
Our intel on Shuto says he gets sloppy when
a bout doesn't go the way he expects it to.
データによると
首藤ってヤツは—
自分の思いどおりにならねえと
相撲が雑になるらしいしな
そこを突けば
お前にも勝機はあるかもしれねえ
If you can take advantage of that,
you might find a way to win.
Will that really be enough?
（蛍）本当に それで足りますかね
（千比路）うん？
If I faced Shuto in 100 regular bouts,
（蛍）今の僕が
首藤さんと普通にやったら—
100回やっても
100回 僕が負けるでしょう
I don't think I'd win a single one.
So I need to make bout
number 101 an irregular one.
だから
僕は作らないといけないんです
僕が勝てる普通じゃない101回目を
What would annoy you most
if your opponent did it, Kunisaki-san?
國崎(くにさき)さんが相手にやられて—
いちばんムカつくことって
何ですか？
（千比路）
う〜ん…　俺っていうか—
Well, there is something that'd probably
tick off anyone who takes sumo seriously.
真面目にやってるヤツなら
みんな そうだと思うけどよ
Spirit!
はっきよい！
And that would be...
（千比路）ムカつくのは…
（首藤）うん？
Someone who doesn't give a damn.
（千比路）やる気がないヤツが
いちばんムカつくな
Please don't tell anyone what I'm planning.
（蛍）
僕がやろうとしていることは—
みんなに
ナイショにしててくださいね
They'll get mad.
怒られちゃいますから
そう…　仲間を
怒らせるくらいじゃないと—
Yeah...
If it doesn't enrage my own team,
it won't be enough.
多分 僕には足りないですから
Don't worry, Hotaru.
大丈夫だ ホタル　仲間だけは
お前の覚悟を見誤ったりはしねえ！
Your team understands your resolve.
No respect, no ideals,
no audience or sympathy.
（蛍）
憧れも 理想も 観客の同情も—
This hell I've created...
全てを捨てて作り出した
この地獄こそが—
僕が勝てる101回目の土俵！
is my irregular 101st bout!
（真田）首藤の冷静さを奪った！
これが三ツ橋のねらいか！
He got Shuto to lose his temper.
Is that what Mitsuhashi was going for?
（蛍）
ここまでが 勝利のための一矢(いっし)
This was just the first
arrow I'll use to win.
そして これが…
And this is...
（蛍）二の矢！
（首藤）グッ！
...the second!
（桐仁）
猫だまし！　ここでやるかよ！？
Clapping in his face!
What a time to do that!
（加納）首藤！
（首藤）ンンッ…
Shuto!
If he looks away for a moment,
（蛍）一瞬 目を離してくれれば
たどりつける
I can reach it...
A battle I can win!
勝利の土俵に
I don't care how it looks.
不格好でもいい
これが 僕の磨いた三本の矢だ！
This is the technique I've practiced.
My three arrows!
三ツ橋が後ろを取った！
Mitsuhashi got behind him!
You're getting better.
進化してやがる
But what's he going to do now?
（金盛）だが ここから どうする？
Do you have some secret
for moving that mountain?
この山を動かすための
奇策でもあるってのか？
もう奇策なんて要らねえぞ ホタル
You don't need anything special, Hotaru.
Those stomps you did while
watching Hinomaru are a pistol
火ノ丸の背中を見ながら
踏んできた しこは テッポウは—
少しずつだが 確実に
お前を憧れに近づけているんだぜ
that is slowly but gradually
getting you closer to your ideal!
You've trained hard enough to be
able to push him over half a rope!
死ぬ気で鍛えた その体には—
俵半分くらいは越えられる力は
もう あるはずだ！
Go!
（２人）いけー！
（間宮）押せー！
Push!
Win!
（桐仁）勝てーっ！
（小関）三ツ橋！
Mitsuhashi!
Sumo gods, you probably
don't like me very much.
相撲の神さま　あんたは
きっと僕のことなんか嫌いでしょう
何せ あの火ノ丸さんまで
嫌うようなヤツだ
You even hate someone like Hinomaru-san.
So yeah, I've never cared one bit
そんな あんたの顔色なんか
うかがっちゃいないよ 最初から！
about sucking up to you!
But no matter what anyone
says, I need this win!
誰に何を思われようと
この勝利だけは 火ノ丸さんに…
For Hinomaru-san...
チームに届けるんだ！
For my team!
Who won?
どっちだ？
East side wins!
（審判）東の勝ち！
Yes!
No way...
そんな…　物言い！？
A protest?
After all that?
（桐仁）
ここまで来るのに あいつが
どれだけ積み上げたと思ってんだよ
After all the work he put in?!
Please let the ruling stand!
頼む　軍配どおりであってくれ！
Simultaneous landings! Restart the bout!
同体 取り直し！
ハッ…　三ツ橋？
Mitsuhashi...
まさか…
Don't tell me...
When he fell...
あのとき…
Please don't try to stop me.
（蛍）止めないでくださいね
（桐仁）あっ…
Leaving the ring now won't solve anything.
今 土俵を下りても
何にもならないけど
As long as I'm in the ring,
something good might happen.
土俵に立ってさえいれば
何かが起こるかもしれませんから
Hands on the ground.
（審判）手をついて！
ホタル…
Hotaru...
It doesn't matter what I have to do.
I want to bring home a win for the team.
どんな犠牲を払ってでも
欲しいんです
チームのための１勝が
（審判）はっきよい！
Spirit!
But you can't leap around anymore...
（千比路）もう跳べねえのに
僕だって 日本一を目指すチームの
一員なんだ！
I'm on this team to
make it the best in Japan!
見てろ
Just watch.
いつか 僕の勝利に
感謝するときが来るからな！
Someday, you'll be really thankful when I win!
Bout over.
（審判）勝負あり！　西の勝ち！
West side wins!
Two losses for Odachi. It's do or die now.
（間宮）
大太刀は２連敗　もう あとがない
しかも 次の相手は
国宝 大包平(おおかねひら) 加納彰平
And their next opponent is...
National Treasure Okanehira
AKA Kano Akihira.
（金盛）
天王寺に次ぐ 白楼ナンバー２
Hakuro's number two behind Tennoji.
Which means he's also the number
two high school sumo wrestler.
…ということは
今の高校相撲界において—
ナンバー２ということだ
（加納）勝ったのに浮かない顔だな
You don't look happy about winning.
That turn, that clap, and that leap...
あの突っかけも
猫だましも 八艘(はっそう)飛びも—
He must've trained pretty hard.
相当 稽古してきたんだろう
He loves sumo enough to
give it everything he had.
本当に相撲が好きで
全てを懸けて…
But...
ただ勝てなきゃ 結局 無意味
If you can't win, it's meaningless.
努力ってのは
勝って初めて評価される
You only get praised for your
hard work after you've won.
No matter what path they took to get there,
the winner's path is the right one.
それまで
どんな道を歩んでこようが—
勝ったヤツの道が正しいんだ
You won.
お前は勝った　そのことを
素直に喜んどけばいいんだ
Just be glad that you did.
（アナウンス）
中堅戦 東 國崎君　西 加納君
Third bout.
On the east side, Kunisaki-kun.
On the west side, Kano-kun.
（蛍）ハァハァ…
すみません みんな　すみません！
I'm sorry, guys. I'm sorry!
So you still can't win a bout, Hotaru!
結局 最後まで
勝てねえんじゃねえか ホタル
（審判）おい 君！
Hey, now...
I've got pretty sharp ears,
so I caught what you were saying over there.
（千比路）俺は耳がいいからよ
あんたの話も よ〜く聞こえたぜ
確かに あんたの言うとおり—
It's true what you said...
勝負ってのは相手を否定し
自分を肯定するためのもんだ
Competition is all about rejecting
your opponent and affirming yourself.
Hotaru trained hard to win,
but he couldn't pull it off.
ホタルは勝つために努力してきたよ
でも 勝てなかった　全敗だよ
He's never won a bout.
結果だけ見りゃ
いても いなくても一緒
If you go by results, it doesn't
matter if he's here or not.
何もしてないのと一緒だ
He'd have the same tally if he just sat out.
But you know, when I'm by his side,
seeing just how hard he works,
でもな 横で あいつの努力を
ずっと見てたら—
それが全て無意味なんて
俺は思わねえし—
I know his efforts aren't meaningless,
and I won't let anyone say they are!
誰にも そんなことは言わせねえ！
Hotaru, I'm grateful.
ホタル　感謝するぜ
If I were in your situation...
俺が お前と同じ立場だったら—
素人のぶんざいで チームのために
日本一のチームを相手に—
As a newbie, would I have
put the team before myself?
Would I have tried to get a dirty win
against the best team in Japan?
どんな みっともねえマネしてでも
勝ちてえと思えただろうか？
I'm a genius.
俺は天才だ
今まで 息をするように勝ってきた
Winning is like breathing for me.
But today, you reminded me
でも 今日
ホタルに改めて教えられたぜ
how cool it is to work for your win,
regardless of how it looks to everyone else.
なりふりかまわず
食らいついていくカッコよさをな
Dachi High is facing elimination,
ダチ高は今 絶体絶命だ
but we're not giving up.
でも 諦めねえ
あいつの努力を否定させねえために
We won't let his hard work go to waste.
You'd do the same, right?
お前だって そうだろう？
You're all fired up to show Tennoji
he's not on the wrong path.
負けた天王寺の道が間違ってると
思いたくなくて—
燃えているんだろうが
Hinomaru's path and Hotaru's path
aren't meaningless.
火ノ丸の道も ホタルの道も
無意味じゃねえ
And I, along with Hotaru's fire
which now burns inside me,
それを
ホタルに熱をもらった俺が—
am gonna win and prove it to you!
てめえに勝って 証明してやるよ！
So this is a wheelchair
meant for sumo wrestlers...
さすが力士用の車イス
It's huge.
（３人）でかい…
Next Bout    "Weak Spirit, Strong Will"